[Music]
of all the terrible things about our
diets high dietary sodium intake high
salt intake is the leading risk
estimated to be causing millions of
deaths every year
killing millions mainly through adverse
effects on blood pressure an increased
risk of stroke heart attack and kidney
damage
hypertension high blood pressure still
called the silent and invisible killer
because it really causes symptoms but is
one of the most powerful independent
predictors of some of our leading causes
of death
we evolved consuming a diet very rich in
potassium and low in sodium but today
this pattern has been completely
reversed this flip reflects a shift from
traditional plant-based diets high in
potassium and low in sodium a shift from
fruits greens roots and tubers to salty
processed foods stripped of potassium
which is considered a nutrient of public
health concern because 98 of the u.s
population doesn't even reach the
recommended minimum daily intake of
potassium as i mentioned in the last
video
and low potassium intake itself is
implicated in high blood pressure and
cardiovascular disease yet few
physicians actually think about
proposing their patients eat more foods
that are potassium rich like fruits and
vegetables to better control blood
pressure even though several
meta-analyses have now confirmed that
high potassium intake appears to reduce
the risk of stroke
there's even a reduction in stroke risk
independent of blood pressure effects
consistent with other protective effects
of potassium such as reducing clot
formation
reducing hardening of the arteries
reducing the generation of free radicals
higher sodium intake is associated with
a 20 increased risk of dying prematurely
where higher potassium intake was
associated with 20 reduced risk of dying
prematurely
yeah but sodium is found in crappy
processed foods while potassium is
concentrated in healthy foods like beans
and greens so having a low sodium intake
and high potassium intake may just be a
marker for more healthful diet more
plant foods and less crap
how do we know sodium has caused an
effect bad because randomized controlled
trials show sodium reduction leads to
blood pressure reduction
just like they're randomized controlled
trials showing that if you give people
extra potassium you can bring down their
blood pressures as well
so what about using potassium chloride
to salt your food rather than sodium
chloride
that's what's found in these zero sodium
salt substitutes potassium chloride is a
naturally occurring mineral salt which
is obtained the same way we get regular
sodium salt since we get too much sodium
and not enough potassium this would seem
to make potassium chloride a win-win
solution
now whole healthy plant foods would be
the best way to increase potassium
intake fruits and vegetables have all
sorts of other good things in them
besides potassium but we have 10 studies
now randomized controlled trials showing
that just swapping in some potassium
chloride for regular salt can lead to
significant reductions in blood pressure
and people with hypertension suggesting
that salt substitutes may even help
prevent hypertension as well we know
salt substitutes can lower blood
pressure but does it actually decrease
the incidence of hypertension and more
importantly disease endpoints like
stroke and mortality you don't know
until you
put it to the test in a randomized
controlled trial households had their
salt replaced with just a quarter
potassium chloride at that level most
people either can't tell the difference
or even prefer the salt with the
potassium mixed in
okay but did it actually do any good
the use of even the quarter salt
substitute was associated with cutting
the risk of developing hypertension in
half
okay but what about actually following
people out to see if there's any change
in the risk of dying from cardiovascular
disease
five kitchens in a veteran's retirement
home were randomized into two groups for
about two and a half years salting meals
with regular salt or unbeknownst to the
cooks in the diners a 50-50 blend of
potassium chloride
those in the half-potassium group cut
their risk of dying from cardiovascular
disease by about 40 percent and lived up
to nearly a year longer the life
expectancy difference at age 70 was
equivalent to that which would have
naturally occurred in 14 years meaning
that just switching to half potassium
salt appeared effectively make people
more than a decade younger when it came
to risk of death
as we speak there's a massive randomized
controlled trial wrapping up in china
involving 600 villages more than 20 000
people that'll give us an idea of just
how low we can drop stroke risk with
this
strategy china is perfect because up to
75 of their sodium intake comes from
salt they add in the home kitchen or
dining room whereas most sodium in the
american diet comes pre-packaged in the
meat and processed foods we buy though
certainly the food companies could
switch over themselves why haven't they
and why haven't more people embrace
these salt substitutes if they work well
and can taste just as good
we could be achieving the benefits of a
high potassium paleolithic diet without
the toxicity so is salt substitution
ready for prime time or what
what about safety yes there are
convincing arguments about the benefits
but what about the risks like
you know the quote unquote inclusion of
potentially fatal salt substitutes in
the food supply wait what
we'll talk about the potential downsides
next
[Music]
you